<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copies of several letters, which were delivered to the King being written by sundry friends in the truth, who wrote them as they were moved by the Holy Ghost, from sundry parts of the nation, though unknown one to another : all which being composed together, and having not wholly done their service unto several sober minded people in the nation who have desired to look into the things that were communicated by us to the king : it is therefore thought fit and convenient to publish them to the nation, being a work of the light, wrote by the movings of the Spirit of Truth, that the nation may see what visitations, instructions, warnings and tender invitations the King hath already had by and from the servants of the Lord, and such as with the peace and well governement of the nation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40152</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12131665</idno>
  <idno type="VID">54755</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240960997</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3688</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12131665</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54755)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 594:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copies of several letters, which were delivered to the King being written by sundry friends in the truth, who wrote them as they were moved by the Holy Ghost, from sundry parts of the nation, though unknown one to another : all which being composed together, and having not wholly done their service unto several sober minded people in the nation who have desired to look into the things that were communicated by us to the king : it is therefore thought fit and convenient to publish them to the nation, being a work of the light, wrote by the movings of the Spirit of Truth, that the nation may see what visitations, instructions, warnings and tender invitations the King hath already had by and from the servants of the Lord, and such as with the peace and well governement of the nation.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letters are signed by George Fox, Alexander Parker, James Naylor, Henry Fell, John Sowter, William Smith, William Caton, and G.W. [i.e. George Whitehead].</note>
                  <note>Wing enters work under George Fox.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54755:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54755:1"/>
            <p>THE COPIES OF Several Letters, which were delivered to the KING.</p>
            <p>BEING Written by sundry Friends in the Truth, who wrote them as they were moved by the Holy Ghost, from sundry parts of the Nation, though unknown one to another; all which being composed together, and having not wholly done their service unto several sober minded people in the Nation who have desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to look into the things that were communicated by us to the King, It is therefore thought fit and convenient to publish them to the Nation, being a work of the light, wrote by the movings of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, that the Nation may see what Visitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Instructions, Warnings and tender Invitations the King hath already had by and from the servants of the Lord, and such as wish the Peace and well Government of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the signe of the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Aldersgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:54755:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54755:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the Power of the Lord God rule, that with that you may be preserved, and stand from doing any thing, or suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be done (under you, or in your name) which may be to the overturning of you; for you see how the Lord hath brought down and overturned by his Secret Arm and Hand, for we have seen the Hand of the Lord in overturning every change that hath been overturned these many years, and they have been warned by us before they were overturned by the hand and Power of the Lord; and now is your day and tryal whether you will answer the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the Lord, for which purpose he hath brought you to be a rod to the wicked, and whether you will go beyond your bounds. We are a People that have suffered under every Power, Goods spoyling, Banishment and Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till death; and many now at this time is in Prison, yet there hath been pretence in every Power of Tolleration for them that fear God though different in Judgment. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we do reprove sin in the Gate, and Corruption in Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, and Ministry, and Teachers that be found out of the Life that they were in that gave forth the Scriptures, and for this cause have we been stocked, whipped, and made a prey upon by every hand: And because we could not hold up such things as Tythes, which Christ came to end, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. And hold up such practices as are not found in the Scriptures, Contrary to the Commands of Christ, and deny our selves of the unrighteous practices of the wicked, therefore are we hated of the wicked for these things, but we can say the Lord forgive them.</p>
            <p>And Now Friends, you being come into the Power, and we hearing that there is Tolleration proclaimed, and yet there is much violence and persecution, as though the Nation would rise up in a Massacring, breaking up Meetings of the People that meet together in the Worship and Service of the Lord, and to build up themselves in their most holy Faith, praying in the holy Ghost; which things are a dishonor to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; for when things are done by a cleer Law and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54755:3"/> and people are not fallen upon in the high Waies and private places, which is not a Credit to Government. And Now Friends we have been made a prey upon for and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Governments, which the Lord God his hand is turned against; therefore as I said before, it is your day and time to do mercy, and to walk humbly with God, that is that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of you. In the daies of <hi>Oliver</hi> Protector they put forth the Oath of Abjuration, which was put forth to be taken by them which was Popishly affected; and though they knew that Friends was against Popery, yet they made a prey upon them because they could not take an Oath; yet they knew themselves that they could not swear, but obey the Doctrine of Christ, who ends the swearing in old time, And said let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay, in all your communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And then there was another thing came out which was concerning Rogues and sturdy Beggars, which men of 40, 50, and 60, l. a year was whipped as sturdy beggars, that honest men could hardly pass up and down to see their Friends and do their outward occasions; and besides, many honest women have been whipped upon the same account. And now there is an Oath of Allegiance that hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to some of our Friends, and they know that Friends cannot take an Oath, so there is yet likely a prey to be made upon Friends that abides in the Doctrine of Christ; We seek the Peace, Good and Welfare of all men, and are not against any mans person, neither do we wrestle with Carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, but Spiritual; Neither have we been found in Plots or things against any Power, or is it our intent but that all might live Peaceably in the fear of God, as knowing that God can overturn them with his hand that do not do justly; And now the Cry is, that we are against the King, we are against the King, Which thing is not so, for they have smal reason to think so, for he hath done us no hurt; for whosoever Rules in Righteousness God will accept, that we know. We have given our backs to every Profession, and our Cheeks to every Power that hath risen up, yet we never resisted with Carnal Weapons, and can say the Lord forgive them, and turn them the other Cheek, and sees that all that doth strike about Religion with Carnal Weapons are not spiritual men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Fox.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54755:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>KING CHARLES,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou came not into this Nation by Sword, neither by Victory of War, but by the Power of the Lord; Now if thou do not live in it thou wilt not prosper; and if the Lord hath shewed thee mercy and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee, and if thou dost not shew mercy and forgive, the Lord God will not hear thy Prayers, nor them that pray for thee; and if thou do not stop Persecution and Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and take away all Laws that do hold up Persecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion, but if thou persist in them, and uphold Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, they will make thee as blind as all that have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, for persecution was ever blind, and God by his Power and by his hand overthrows and bringeth Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his oppressed, and doth his valiant acts; and if thou dost bear the Sword in vain, and let Drunkenness, Oaths, Pleasure, May-games with Fidlers, Drums, Trumpets, and set up May-poles with the Image of a Crown on top of them, Abominations, the Nations will quickly turn to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah,</hi> and as bad as the old World which grieved the Lord, and he overthrew them, and so he will you, if these things be not suddenly prevented hardly; was there so much wickedness at liberty before now as this is now at this day, as though there were no Terror nor Sword of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, which doth not grace a Government nor is a praise to them that do well; So our prayers is for them that be in Authority, that we may live a Godly life in which we have Peace, and that we may not be brought into Ungodliness by them. So hear and consider, and do good in the time whilest thou hast Power, and be merciful and forgive, and that is the way to overcome and obtain the Kingdom of Christ.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:54755:4"/>
            <head>To <hi>CHARLES</hi> late Proclaimed KING.</head>
            <p>FRiend, keep peace among people of all sorts different in judgements, that one may not destroy another about Religion, but let them have their meetings together, and one confer with another, and have Meetings a purpose, and Places, and none excepted: And that <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> all may have Liberty to speak forth their mind, and then let them that be Ministers of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, Convince, and Convert, and stop the mouths of Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayers, and war with Spiritual Weapons and Spiritual Warr, and be thou Chief Magistrate to keep peace among them how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; and take heed of the Priests, for they will strive to make Thee their Executioner to execute their malice upon such as they are not able to resist their spirits, and if Thou do'st not fulfil their wills they will slight and not matter Thee: For this is the word of the Lord God to Thee, be still and patient in the Wisdom of the Lord God, until that go over all, and to order with that; and mark what became of the <hi>Jews</hi> that turned against Christ, and what became of <hi>Herod</hi> that persecuted the Christians, and what became of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Host that oppressed the People of God, and what became of the false Prophet, Beast, and Dragon, with all their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling worships since the dayes of the Apostles, must they not go into the fire; and all Religions which Was held up with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weapons in the Law Christ ends, and rebukes the zeale of them that would destroy, and told them that he came to save mens lives and not to destroy them; and the Apostles wrestled not with flesh and blood and carnal weapons, nor did not carnally war with people and imprison them; but they that did preach the Gospel they were in the end of the Law, and their weapons were spiritual and so was their war, and so they were to love enemies, and this was spoken to the Apostles, which never went to complain to Magistrates to have them to persecute; for they do not love enemies that do so; for they that love enemies are the spiritual-weaponed men, and differs from the Jews which held up their Religion by sword &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54755:4"/> Law which Christ ends, and the Faith and Church stands in the end of the Law, for Christ is the end of the Law for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness sake to every one that believes, who are Members of him his Body the Church, of which he is the Head, and in it Priest, King, and Prophet; The World may make Kings and destroy them again, and put on Earthly Crowns and take them off again, which they have done since the Apostles daies; but mind Christ making thee a King, and giving thee a Crown which is immortal and lasts for ever, In which is the power of a World without end, and of an everlasting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Dominion, which is without end; therefore mind the Raign of Christ, and be subject to him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend and Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LEt no one be persecuted for Church, Worship and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let no Carnal Weapons meddle with that among Christians; but it hath been the Practice of the Jews, Apostati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Christians and Heathens, which was not the practice of the Apostles before the Apostasie; for their weapons was spiritual, therefore spiritual weaponed men that is in the power of God with Spiritual weapons wrestle, and not with carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, for that is a carnal war, those cannot be called Ministers of the Gospel, or spiritual men, that have not spiritual wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, which makes to differ from Papists, Heathens and Jews; the Jews used carnal weapons, and the Law tollerated them; and they was to be killed that would not hear the Priest, and they was to be stoned to death, presumptuous Blasphemers and false Prophets was to be run through; but Christ who destroyes the Devil the Author of Presumptuous ones, Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers and false Prophets, he ends the Jews Law, and saves mens lives; They that follow this Captain, their weapons are not carnal, but spiritual, and they wrestle not with flesh and blood, and destroyes no mans life, but Christ ends the Jews Law that did. And consider what <hi>Moses</hi> said that had the Law that went over all Transgressors; To this chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate there came a Complaint that there was prophesying in the Camp, and <hi>Moses</hi> instead of prisoning them as Tumultuous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54755:5"/> and breakers of the Peace, said, Enviest thou for my sake? would all the Lords People were Prophets; so Magistrates of understanding rebukes such complainers; therefore come nigh unto the Law that ye may be like <hi>Moses,</hi> which is far from the Gospel: The patience of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> hath been wanting, who said, Let them alone, if it be of God it will stand: and this was to them who was eager of prisoning and persecuting the Saints and true Christians, from whom there is no example to persecute any for Religion, or put to death with Carnal Weapons, for that is it which brought Christendom into heaps, and into a Wilderness, by which the Spirit hath been quenched, and prophesie despised, and the Order of the true Church lost, in which there is comfort in edification and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that is, if any thing be revealed to him that sits by, let the first hold his peace, for ye may all prophesie one by one, the Spirit of the Prophets was subject to the Prophets, and this was Order in all the Churches of God, which is counted Disorder, and breaking Peace, and a Law against it since the Apostles daies in this which is called Christendom, by which mens Spirits hath been tied up, and limited from Edification and Comforting, and Prophecying, and that which hath been invented by men set up and tollerated; therefore let all your Laws be to keep Peace among the people that they do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy one another, but an equal Justice be amongst all, and in the Power of God, or else that will overthrow you; and living in that you will have unity with God and all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and let no prophane man, Drunkard, Swearer, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutor bear Office, for they will cry Peace, Peace, until upon them come sudden Destruction; therefore in the Fear of the Lord keep that you may receive his Wisdom from above, by which all things was made, that ye may order all things to his Glory with that Wisdom which is pure and gentle; and consider that <hi>Nebuchadonezer</hi> that great Tree under whom the Beasts of the Field sheltered, he knew not the Kingdom of the most High Ruling in men; Therefore mind that Kingdom, and that will let no Beasts shelter under you; and consider <hi>Cain</hi> was the first Persecutor about Religion and Sacrifice; and they that be born of the flesh which have gotten the Scriptures, and are out of the Spirit that gave them forth, will persecute them that are born of the Spirit, which they that are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54755:5"/> born of the Spirit never persecuted any, and all those that runneth up and down with packets of letters, are like <hi>Saul</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Saints, and not like <hi>Paul</hi> with Spiritual Weapons, and are not to be minded, for they would make the Magistrates their Executioners, for which cause Gods hand is turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them; The time is come that they must acknowledge their blind zeal, as <hi>Paul</hi> did when he was <hi>Saul,</hi> who persecuted others about Religion, but it may be said, if any be of a people and disent from that people, they may kill them and put them to death, the <hi>Papists, Turks, Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> may say so, but Christ and the Apostles, and true Church of old did not say so, nor do so, but said let him be as a <hi>Heathen,</hi> or have no company with him, but love Enemies, and if he hunger feed him, and thats the way to overcome him with love, that hath been wanting among those that are called Christians, who hath almost starved and pined many of our friends in Prison, And would neither visit them themselves nor suffer others, and this is our measure we have received from them, to whom we have given our backs and cheeks, which yet stands ready for the smiter; Now if they go into everlasting punishment, and stand on the left hand of Christ, that doth not visit Christ in Prison, what will become of them that casts him in Prison where he is manifest, will not all in the least measure of truth judge that they be out of the Power of God, though they have the form? let not them be persecuted who are taught of God, for not paying anothers Minister which they know to be false, and for not repairing other meeting Places, and not paying Clerks for saying Amen, and turning the Hour-glass, and hanging the Pulpit, and such like Service, but every one maintain his own Minister that will have them; Let there be no compulsion about such things, but a free People, a free Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry ruled by the law of Love; and this is the way to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all spirits in the World, that in the dignity hath the honour; And let no men be persecuted for obeying the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apostles &amp; Christ, that saith swear not at all, not by Heaven nor by Earth, nor any other Oath, but saith let your yea be yea, and your nay nay, whatsoever is more then these is evil; Let not them be persecuted who practice this, whose yea and nay is more then oaths, which is Christs Doctrine, who ends the Prophets and the Law, and first Priesthood, and first
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54755:6"/> Covenant, and <hi>Moses,</hi> and the Vail, who is greater then <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and reigns over the House of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Joseph,</hi> to whom the Angels must bow; Now he who is Christ saith, swear not at all, though these sware and commanded swearing, and though men in strife sware which was for the ending of it, Christ who destroyes the (Devil the author of strife) saith swear not at all, but let your Yea be yea, and your Nay nay; And he that teaches this Doctrine is the first and the last; so let no one be persecuted that will do truth at yea and nay; This is according to Christs Doctrine and Scriptures of Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>O KING.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GReat hath been the Love of God towards Thee, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to be prized and never to be forgotten by Thee, who by a secret hand hath preserved Thee in many great straits and dangers, and now after many years travailes and tryals in strange Countreys and forreign Kingdoms, hath the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God by a wonderfull Providence brought Thee back again, into thy own Native Nation, and set thee in place of great Power, as King and Supream Ruler over so great and large People, and much more hath the Lord done for thee; And now O King! what doth the Lord require of Thee, even this, that thou shouldest do justly and love mercy, and walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with God; Humility is a precious Ornament, such an Ornament as Jesus Christ the King of kings did daily wear, and exhorted even all his subjects to follow him, &amp; to learn of him, for saith he I am meek and lowly in heart, and ye shall find rest unto your Souls, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. And the wise King <hi>Solomon</hi> did prefer Humility before Honour, as it is written, the fear of the Lord is the instruction of Wisdom, and before Honour is Humility, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.33. This is the true Honour which abides, which follows Humility; He that humbles himself shall be exalted and honoured by the Lord, but there is an honour which abides not, which men would have before they have learned Humility, and that is the honour of men
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54755:6"/> which they seek and receive one of another; And much of this kind thou wilt find amongst men in these daies, which God will blast, and lay it all in the dust, for therein lies a great snare. And as thy Souls friend I do declare unto thee, that if thou let that enter and receive the honour of men into thy heart, it will choak the good seed in thee, and stop the current of the streams of Heavenly love, and thou wilt become dry and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, and empty of the good fruits of Righteousnesse, which if thou dwell in the humility of Christ, and receive the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Truth into thy heart, then thou wilt be kept open and tender, and the seed of Righteousnesse will grow in thee, and the true love of God will spring up in thy heart, and make thee truly faithful unto God, and a blessing unto his People; Remember the saying of Christ, <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.4. I receive not honour from men; and further he said in verse 44. How can ye believe which receive honour one of another, and seek not the honour that cometh from God only; The Lord keep thee out of all the snares of the great enemie who goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout like a roaring Lyon seeking whom he may devour.</p>
            <p>There is a people in <hi>England,</hi> who appear not unto thee in that kind of high titles, or outward honour (as many do) who in their hearts wish well unto Thee, and desire thy prosperity and peace in Christ; And the effectual fervent prayers of Righteous men fearing God may work more for thy good and safety, then all the fair words and swords of ungodly men. We are a people whom the God of Heaven hath gathered by his holy Arm into the fold of the good Shepherd; and even in troublesome times when we were scattered up and down, and wandering astray did the Lord visit us, and revealed that life and power of truth in our hearts, which many years we had been (vainly) seeking without us, the power of which did mightily work in us, destroying sin and the works of the Devil, and forming and creating us a new in Christ Jesus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good works; And as the Lord had made us pertakers of the riches of his love, and satisfied our souls with the fatnesse and fulnesse of his house, a necessity did the Lord lay upon many of us to declare unto others what great things the Lord hath done for our Soules, inviting others to come freely, that they may be satisfied with the goodnesse and loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Lord; And withal testifying against pride and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54755:7"/> and other evils which have abounded amongst most sorts of people, as well Rulers &amp; Teachers as others: And for this Testimony which we have born for several years, we have been greatly hated, reviled, mocked, stoned, whipped, stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, persecuted and imprisoned, and looked upon by many as troublers of the Nation, as formerly it was said of the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God; for example, when <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Orator ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 24. he spoke on this wise, <hi>We have found this man a pestilent fellow, a mover of Sedition, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of the Nazarenes;</hi> so it was said then, and thus it is said now, many hard speeches are spoken against us, but O King try us thorrowly, and if falseness, treachery, or unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness be found in us or any of us, then let such suffer, and not be spared; But if upon Tryal we be found sincere, true and faithful to God, and just and upright in our dealings amongst men, then spare us, and grant us our Natural Right, which is liberty of our Consciences in the worship of God, without limitting the Spirit of God, for God is free and will not be limitted to this or that form or way which men set up, but in his own Way, even in Spirit and Truth, by men of upright hearts will he be worshipped. And O King, even to this day are we reviled and persecuted, and neither suffered to have the liberty of our Consciences, nor the liberty of our bodies; for of late time as it pleased God who is my Light and Leader to order me his servant, whom he hath called into the work of the Ministry, to come into <hi>Cheshire,</hi> where I walked peaceably and in the fear of God, on the 17th day of the 3d month, being at a Meeting where many of Gods people were in the fear of God assembled together, and even while I was Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string the Word of Life unto the people, there came in some Souldiers with Swords and Pistols, and haled me (a servant of God) forth of the Meeting, and afterwards fetched forth some others of the Neighbours, and brought us before some of the Commissioners, and though nothing was or could justly be laid to my charge of any evil done, nor intended to be done, yet because I could not for Conscience sake enter into Recognizance and subscribe an Engagement, as being made free by Christ, they committed me to the Marshals, under whose custody I have been Prisoner these 24 dayes, and since they have committed eight more of my Friends who did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54755:7"/> their willingness to submit to all just things, and are ready to do any lawful service under thee as King and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Ruler; and withal desiring the benefit of thy late De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, wherein thy tenderness is expressed towards ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Consciences, yet because for Conscience sake they could not subscribe such an Engagement as was tendered to them, they yet remain Prisoners under the custody of Martial men, and are kept from their Wives and Children.</p>
            <p>These things I was pressed in spirit to lay before thee, that if God put it into thy heart, a few words from thee might easily stop this kinde of proceeding against a people fearing God; this way of proceeding is not onely in this County, but also in many others; sorely have many of our Friends suffered of late time, the hearing of which if it were related might make a tender heart even to bleed. We are a great People scattered up and down the Nation, and our cause and case is one, so that what thou dost for one thou dost it for all; I write in plainness to thee, not daring to give thee flattering titles, but declaring the Truth from my heart, assuring thee that we are Gods People, and the sheep of his pasture; so what thou dost, do it as unto and for the Lord, that of the Lord thou mayest have a reward. Power is now committed into thy hand; The God of Heaven direct thy heart in true wisdom, to use thy power to Gods glory, the good of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the comfort of thy own Soul, Which is the prayer and earnest desire of a servant of Christ, who loves thy Soul, and desires thy happiness in this world, and in the World to come Live everlasting.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ALEXANDER PARKER.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Namptwich <hi>in</hi> Cheshire, <hi>the place of my confinement,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 10th <hi>day of the</hi> 4th <hi>month,</hi> 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>O KING,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GOD hath in these Nations a People gathered by himself into his Light, who are known to himself
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54755:8"/> better then to men, and therefore have we suffered by men under all the powers that have risen in this Nation, ever since God called us towards himself by his eternal Light and Spirit; and though we receive not our Laws from man, yet are we not without Law as to our God, but have one Law-giver, even Christ Jesus our Lord, our Life, and our Head, blessed over all, and from his Laws we may not depart, and by his Law in our Conscience, and the Power of his Spirit in our hearts are we ordered and guided to walk holily towards our God, and harmelesly towards men, as the Saints of old witnessed in Scripture, however they be minded towards us, and by the vertue of the Lamb, and not of flesh and blood, are we made to give our goods to the spoil, and our bodies to the tortures of cruel men, rather then defile our Consciences, or sin against any one of the least of the Commands of our Lord and Law-giver Christ Jesus, who by the light of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit doth daily lead us out of the evils and vanity of this present world, and having begotten us into his own guiding, he doth not suffer us to subject our selves to any thing whatsoever is not set up by himself, nor to worship the god of this world, nor obey him in commands or customs, but the exercise of our Consciences he hath redeemed wholly to himself, and by his precious blood hath sprinkled them, and made them tender, and pure, so that we may not worship false gods nor the true God in a false manner, nor may we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship men, nor follow the customs of Nations, Kindreds, or People, or Languages, but the Spirit of Truth it self we must follow, nor may we break Christs Commands in swearing, when men commands us, but must obey him who saith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> nor may we joyn to or uphold any worship whatsoever, but what the Spirit of truth it self leads us into, though many have sought to force us thereto, nor may we leave the Ministry of Christ, and that maintenance which the Gospel allows of, to maintain a Priesthood with Tithes, and so go back from Christ to the Law, that the Apostle saith is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annulled, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>And for such things as these, concerning a tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and the Law of our God, have we suffered grievous persecution, and not for any unrighteousness done by us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any mans person or estate; nor have we suffered by any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54755:8"/> just Law of the Nation, but by the wills of cruel men, and as a prey to every mans lust hath been our liberties, lives and estates, and the Rulers that have been to this day have not sought our deliverance, but have dealt treacherously with us, and the Lord whom we serve hath seen it and reproved it, and yet we are not set free, but at this day we live in the account of the rude and envious people, as a people appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to death and desolation, and the whole body of ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, and rage of wickedness is upon us daily, &amp; with cruelty falls upon us in our persons &amp; estates, and our peaceable Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings to worship the living God; and as to all these things we are laid as the mire in the street for every rude boy to run o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and we have not found help from man, as to all the powers that have been till this day since we were a people, nor do we speak this, because we look for help from man, nor indeed can we expect that from men, until men own the same principle of God to rule in them to which we are subject, which is the Son of Righteousness, and leads all into Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, Truth and Peace that his Light doth follow, who is known to us to be King of Kings, and Judge of the Judges, though flesh and blood sees not his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And now O King, as we have been moved of the Lord in bowels of love, and with much plainness of speech (after the Spirit of Truth, and not with vain complements) to lay these things before all the several powers that have risen hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, with several other evils which our God hath sent us to testifie against (both in Rulers, Teachers, and People) so we have done, and for that we have suffered also for a witness against them as it is at this day; so the same God hath now after a while put into our hearts to lay these things before thee (O King) that thou mayest not be ignorant to what we are called, and for what we suffer, &amp; in this we rejoice that we feel love to thy Soul even while we are thus doing, and if many should be moved hereto of God, take heed of being wearied therewith, nor count it clamour or trouble, as they that was before thee did, and so let up prejudice and evil thoughts in their own hearts against the innocent; for this we say unto thee, and affirm in the Name of our God, that the more any are (tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) moved by the eternal Spirit to warn thee of these things
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54755:9"/> (or any other evils that may any way grieve his holy Spirit) so much doth the Lord (of thy life, and true, and everlasting peace) double his love unto thee, and show his willingness to stay thee from that which hath removed Kings, and broken Kingdoms; and this we know to be in God, and by him in us towards thy Soul and eternal well-fare. And though we cannot Swear, and Unswear, Covenant, and Uncovenant with every change that comes, as men do that know not the everlasting Covenant and Decree of God; yet this hath God sealed in our hearts, to seek the good of all men, plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst none, but study to live quietly, and exercise our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science faithfully towards whatever Government our God shall set up, desiring that all men in their day may so use their power, as they may give account to God with joy, and not leave their names for a curse and reproach among men; for this we know, that God is now at hand to give a speedy reward to every man as shall be the work of his day.</p>
            <p>Wherefore O King seek the fear of the Lord, and not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, do Justice and Judgement in this thy day, relieve the helpless, oppressed, and break the yoak of bondage that lyes upon the poor, and bring Judgement into the Gates, and let not Justice be sold, least the meek of the earth cry to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee; verily God is nearer this Nation to avenge then many can believe, though he have done wonders in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that many generations have not seen, and he is trying all sorts of people with the Testimony of his appearance; blessed are they whose eye is open to discern the signs of the times, for a work is God working in the earth, and he will cut it short in Righteousness for his Elect sake which daily hath waited upon him thats blessed for ever.</p>
            <p>O King, spend not thy time in fleshly pleasures, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther strive after that glory which will fade away, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thy heart to God, and wait to feel his Spirit in thee, giving thee light and understanding to guide thy wayes before him, for onely blessed is he who Rules by his Power, and who is taught of God shall be establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Righteousness, and be far from oppession, and onely such shall be called the blessed of God to all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54755:9"/> read, and remember the Righteous and the Wicked.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From one of those whom the world calls</hi> Quakers, JAMES NAYLOR.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Written the 3d day of the 4th month, 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To CHARLES King of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> From one who is in Prison, a Sufferer for the Testimony of his Conscience, and for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions sake.</head>
            <p>FOrasmuch as the Lord God of Heaven and Earth hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee the Supream Authority, and power (according to man) over these Nations, and set thee up again who was thrown down, and given thee Dominion over thine Enemies, even contrary to what thou couldest have expected in some Months past, and in such a way as could hardly have entered into thy thoughts, to obtain that which so long hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from thee without the shedding of blood (which shews that the Lord doth not delight in the shedding of mans blood Therefore do not thou delight in that, nor forget the Lord who hath done this for thee, neither let it slip out of thy minde, least thou shouldst exalt thy self, and in thy heart say, My own hand hath done this, or by my own wisdom or power is this thing come to pass, and so the Lord should not have the praise and the honour which is due alone unto him: Oh! therefore that his fear may be in thy heart (O King) which is the beginning of the true wisdom, whereby thou maist know and understand for what end the Lord hath done this for thee, and so mayest come to do the thing which the Lord doth require of thee; namely, to do Justly, to love Mercy, and to walk Humbly with God, and to pay thy Vowes unto the Lord, and to do the things which thou hast promised un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, and in so doing the Lord will establish thy Throne, and preserve thee out of the hands of thy enemies at home and abroad, and make thee a dread and a terrour to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54755:10"/> about thee, and the generations to come may call thee blessed, and the remembrance of thy name will be better then those who went before thee, who have not served the Lord in their generations, but have served themselves and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten him, and so he became their enemy.</p>
            <p>And now is the time of thy Tryal, and the day of thy visita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein the Lord is come to try and to prove what is in thy heart, to see now if thou wilt do that which is Just and Right in his sight, and fear before him, and walk in the way of the Lord, and become a blessing to the Nations. But if now (on the contrary) after the Lord hath done this for thee thou shouldst forget the Lord, and cast his Righteous Law behinde thy back, and shouldst hearken unto evil coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, to do that which is evil in the sight of the Lord, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thy heart against him (as King <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did when he would not let Israel go out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to serve the Lord) and should say in thine heart, who is the Lord that I should fear him or obey him? Even he who hath raised thee up into the Throne of thy Father (which was taken away from him) and hath given thee Dominion over thine enemies, if thou shouldst reject the Lords Counsel, and dispise his Servants and Messengers who declares the truth to thee) and suffer them to be affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted and persecuted, and evilly entreated by wicked men, and such as are enemies to Truth and Righteousness, and not do that which the Lord God requires of thee, seeing the Lord hath given thee power, and put it into thy hands, that so Truth and Righteousness may raign in the Land, and Justice and true Judgement may be executed, and mercy shewed to the poor and oppressed, the fatherless, widow and strangers, and the cause of the Righteous and Innocent heard and pleaded, and oppression and cruelty and violence removed out of the Land, and persecution of any man for Conscience sake in matters of Religion restrained, and those Laws abolished, that so all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may have free liberty in the exercise of their Consciences towards God, to whom they must stand or fall, and give an account in the last day, with whom there is no respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; for all the Laws by which men are compelled to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, hath been made in the time of Antichrists raign, and the Beast, and false prophets, and false Church (which is the great Whore) and long night of Apostacy, which hath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54755:10"/> been since the dayes of the Apostles, wherein people have been erred from the Spirit, and from the Truth in which God is to be worshipped, who is a Spirit; And not to compel men to this or that outward form, for that doth but make them hypocrites, and not true Christians; and that will not excuse any, nor ever be accepted before the Lord for that which is given or offered up unto the Lord must be free, and his People are a free People, and his grace is free, and his Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is freely to be preached to all; so take heed of those men who make a trade of the Scriptures to preach for filthy lucre, for they will betray thee otherwise, by making Laws to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to worship, for by such hath the compelling worships come in; But the true worship of God is in his Spirit, which is free; and that which would limit the Spirit of God, and binde the Conscience (by outward laws in matters of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and keep in bondage) is not of God nor is not truth, for truth is that which sets free, and gives unto <hi>Caesar</hi> the things which are <hi>Caesars,</hi> and unto God the things that are Gods, that the Lord may have his right (w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is to rule in the Conscience) and every man may have their right from the highest to the lowest; and so hereby the hearts of people would be bowed unto thee (as they were unto King <hi>David</hi>) and joyned unto thee in love, and live at peace one with another, and the blessing, of the Lord would be upon thee, and his powerful presence would be with thee, and he would be thy strength and defence; and so thou wouldst be a blessing to the Nations over which thou art King, for the Lord is coming to do a great work in the earth, which men will hardly believe, though it be declared to them: And this I know, that if thou fear the Lord, and stand in the Counsel of the Lord, he will direct thee to do the thing that is Right and Just in his sight, so that thou mayest prosper.</p>
            <p>But now I say, if after all this, O King! thou shouldst forsake the Lord, and walk contrary unto him, he will walk contrary unto thee; And know assuredly this from the Lord, that then he will turn against thee and become thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and thou shalt not be established nor prosper, for the Lords hand will be against thee to destroy thee; &amp; then it will not be for thy good, nor for the good of the Nations that thou art brought in, but for your hurt, and for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54755:11"/> and shame, and confusion. And this from the Lord I declare unto thee in love, in the truth and uprightness of my heart; therefore let me not be accounted thy enemy, neither do thou refuse to hearken unto the Counsel of the Lord (by the meanest of his Servants) nor stop not thine ear from heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto his true and faithful witness, the light of Christ Jesus in thy Conscience, which convinceth thee of sin, and reproves for it, for this hath no fellowship with unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, nor the works of darkness, nor never consents to any evil in thoughts, in words or deeds; I say, take heed of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the Counsel of this, for in so doing thou wilt be given up unto blindness of minde and hardness of heart, and thy understanding will be altogether darkned, and true Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will depart from thee, and thou wilt then give ear unto flatterers, and so wilt do the things (and suffer the things to be done in thy name) for which thou wilt be afterwards reproved and condemned, which will be laid to thy charge, and will be a weight and a burthen too heavy for thee to bear.</p>
            <p>And therefore in time be warned, and hearken diligently that thy Soul may live; for the Lord God of Heaven and Earth is risen to plead with all flesh, who will ease himself of his enemies, and avenge himself upon all his adversaries, and that speedily; for he is now come nigh unto Judgement, who will make a short work in the earth; yea, he will even cut it short in Righteousness, for his own Names sake, his Elect Seeds sake, his annointed which long hath suffered, and for his Peoples sake who have been oppressed, who love the Lord and fear his Name, and walk in his Truth and Righteousness in the uprightness of their hearts, who have long waited upon the Lord for deliverance, and are still made willing to wait upon him in patience (whom we know at length will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliver) for it is from him that we look for deliverance to come in his own time, and by what means as pleaseth him</p>
            <p>And all these overturnings which hath been of late we see plainly, and know the mighty hand of the Lord hath done it, and who will yet bring greater things to pass, for he will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn till Truth and Righteousness comes to raign in King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Nations and Governments, which he alone loves and takes delight in.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54755:11"/>
            <p>And this is the Decree of the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, which is sealed and gone forth, and his determinate Counsel which shall stand for ever, which he is fulfilling now in these latter dayes, according to his promise; and wo from the Lord will be unto all them that decree unrighteous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and take counsel and not at the Lord, for their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel shall not stand (though they dig never so deep to hide it from the Lord) neither shall their Enterprizes come to pass; for no weapon that is formed against the Lord shall prosper, and every tongue that riseth up in Judgement against him shall be condemned; and the Lord will be against all the Kings, and Princes, and Rulers, and Judges of the earth who love not Truth, and Judge not nor Rule not in Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but do turn Judgement backward, and let Truth fall in the streets, and not suffer Equity to enter.</p>
            <p>And this the Lord will do, and the day is now hastning on apace, even for his own Names sake, which long hath been professed by the people in these Nations, but not in Truth and Righteousness have they lived, who have dishonoured it thereby, and caused it to be blasphemed amongst the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, while people have been professing God in words, but in works denying of him, and drawing near unto him with their lips and with their mouths honouring of him, but they have removed their hearts afar off from him, and their fear towards God hath been taught by the precepts of men; but the Precepts of the Lord and his Law in their hearts hath been rejected and not regarded, but they have erred from him in their hearts, and therefore have they not known his wayes.</p>
            <p>And so for this cause is the Lord risen in his mighty Power, and is stretching forth his Arm, and causing his voice to be heard and sounded forth, to plead with the Inhabitants of the earth, and to overturn Kingdoms and Nations, who pulls down Kings, and sets them up at his pleasure; And who may call him to an account? or say what doth he? For by him Kings do raign, and Princes decree Justice; and the hearts of Kings is in the hand of the Lord, as the Rivers of water he turneth them whithersoever he will, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and who do Justice and execute Judgement in the earth shall be honourable, and honoured of the Lord who is getting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self a Name in the earth, and making his Truth honourable,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54755:12"/> and all his Saints who walk in it shall be honourable, as it is written, This honour have all his Saints, who bindes their Kings in Chains, and their Nobles in fetters of Iron; and he will reprove Kings for their sakes.</p>
            <p>For the Lord God is coming to set up his own Kingdome, which stands not in words but in Power, in Righteousnesse, and Peace, and Joy in the holy Ghost, and all the Kingdoms of the world shall become the Kingdoms of his Son Jesus Christ, who is the annointed of the Father to be King of kings and Lord of lords; be wise therefore O ye Kings! be instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted O ye Judges of the earth! serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice with trembling, kiss the Son least he be angry, and ye perish from the way, &amp;c. For he it is by whom Kings are to Raign, and Princes are to Rule and decree Justice; and blessed and truly happy shall they be alone who Rule for him, and by him in Righteousness, Justice and Equity, for such shall prosper.</p>
            <p>But if any man love not the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be accursed, for such are his enemies, that would not that he should Rule over them (by his Law in their hearts) who must be brought before him, and slain before his face, and none can be able to deliver out of his hands, who hath all Power given him of the Father, both in Heaven and in earth; and God hath committed all Judgement unto the Son, who Judgeth the quick and the dead, and who will give a just reward to every one according to their deeds done in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whether they be good or evil.</p>
            <p>And this O King! is the Word of the Lord to thee, and a warning unto thee from the Lord by his Servant, who in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Lord, and love to thy Soul hath declared this to thee in truth and faithfulness, who shall pray for the Kings as Supream, and them that are in Authority, which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, that we may live a quiet and peaceable life in all godliness and honesty; and if otherwise this liberty cannot be enjoyed, I am freely given up to suffer for the Truths sake, in which I have believed, whatsoever the Lord shall please to call me unto, and do rejoice in the Lord, that I am counted worthy to suffer for his Name sake.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Written by one who seeks the good of all men, and the hurt of none, who am a Prisoner for the Truths sake, called</hi> HENRY FELL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:54755:12"/>
               <p>AND furthermore O King! seeing the Lord hath put into thy hands the power and Rule, and Authority to Govern these Nations; and likewise that thou hast declared and given the word of a King for it, That no man shall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in question, or suffer, or be abused, or wronged for diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Opinions in matters of Religion, which do not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb the Peace of the Kingdom; and that there shall be a liberty granted to tender Consciences, and that they shall not suffer or be persecuted for Conscience sake; Therefore do I appeal unto thee for Justice and Equity to be done unto me who have suffered unjustly, and now am at present a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer for Religion, and for Conscience sake (in <hi>Thetford</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> as also are several others of my Friends and Brethren in other parts of the Kingdom) by the corrupt wills of men who are envious, and not according to Law or Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; And the cause (in short) for which I suffer is this, First, I was taken out of a publick Meeting, where we were met peaceably and in the fear of the Lord to wait upon him (and no otherwise, nor for no other end) and committed to Prison by order from the Mayor of this Town (called <hi>John Kendall</hi>) and then after 7 dayes imprisonment I was called before him and the rest of the Magistrates, and because I could not for Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>science sake swear and take the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagance and Supremacy, and because I was a stranger in this place, I was whipped at the Market Cross for a Rogue and Vagrant (though no such thing in the least was proved against me) and sent away with a Pass; and when I had gone some miles from thence, and that the Pass was freely delivered to me by some of those that was to convey me (as the Mayor doth know) to go whither I would, I came back again with it through the Town of <hi>Thetford,</hi> it being in my way whither I was intended to go before; and as I passed through the Town did speak some words to the people, exhorting them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and to fear the Lord, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For which cause was I committed to Prison by a <hi>Mittimus</hi> from the Mayor without any Examination, there to be kept close Prisoner, and not suffered to have a Coppy of the <hi>Mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> where I have now laid several weeks; and now because
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54755:13"/> these things are done in thy name (O King) which are so contrary to Law and Equity, and contrary to what thou hast declared and promised; as that I should be deprived of my liberty and freedom without the breach of any just Law by those which act under thee and in thy name, whereby the Righteous and innocent suffers without cause, and cannot be heard, nor have Justice or Equity. Therefore have I appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto thee, that I may have it from thee, whom the Lord hath set to do Justice, to be a terrour to the evil-doers, and a praise to them that do well: And this is that which the Lord requires of thee, and is good and acceptable in the sight of God, who pleads the cause of the Innocent, whom I know at length will plead my cause if thou refuse to do it; but therein thou wilt not be innocent nor excusable before the Lord, seeing it is laid before thee. So in the will of the Lord I rest, unto whom I commit my cause.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN love to thy Soul the Lord hath drawn forth me towards thee, ever since the day wherein I was made to see this thy day before it was; therefore I am made bold in his power to declare in a measure what he hath made me to see in the light towards thee, to which if thou beest faithfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy name shall be for a praise to the ends of the earth, and thou shalt flourish like a green Bay-tree: Now this is to inform thee of what the Lord hath for thee to do, for there is a prize put into thy hand, and the Lord will if thou rejects not his Counsel, work in, with and by thee, and for his Seeds sake (which thou art to be careful of) which is scattered abroad in the earth, that thou mayest help to bring to pass his work, his great work wch no heart can conceive but such as are brought into a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of that light which expelleth all darkness out of the heart; for the work in hand is suddenly to bring to pass, all the high and potent men of the earth to confusion, all such as hath burthened his Seed, and slain the Just and brought under that which should have brought to him that honour which to him belongeth: Therefore Friend, the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of thee to do Justice, love mercy, and let the oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54755:13"/> go free; for before this thy day hath the faithful and just ones, the Seed of God, the Spirit of Truth in the hearts of the dear Saints of God been kept under, and hath been cut off in many where it hath begun to spring up; for by the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance of the former powers of this Nation hath many of the dear Saints of God in this Nation been exceedingly afflicted, &amp; for no other cause but for bearing their Testimony against the deceit of the wicked practises of ungodly men, such hath been the <hi>Haman</hi>-like spirits of some that hath had power over us, that because we could not for Conscience sake, for fear of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending like <hi>Mordecai,</hi> fulfil their high mindes, as to put off the Hat and bow the knee to them and honour their persons, therefore hath some of us been fined and our goods taken from us, and some have had their bodies cast in Prison; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we could not like <hi>Shedreck, Mesheck</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> fall down and obey what they command us, to wit, Go and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship at the places they require us, and not paying them what they require of us, for such compulsary worship which for the Lords sake in obedience to him we durst not do, therefore have they taken away from some their goods, and some have not onely lost their goods but their bodies laid in Prison, and some have layn there till death, and the reason why we dare not do the things beforesaid, is because we finde them which are called Ministers to be in the steps (many of them) of Anti-christs Ministers, for by their fruits we know them; For can good fruit come out of an evil root, or do men gather grapes of thorns, or figgs on thistles? The tree may be known by its fruits; they call themselves, and the people likewise call them the Ministers of Christ, and yet they know him not, for Christ saith, He that saith he knoweth me and doth not my will, is a lyar; if ye love me saith Christ to his true Ministers, keep my Commandments; hence it appeareth, that he that doth not the Will of Christ doth not know him, and he that doth not keep the Commands of Christ doth not love him, and if they that doth not his Will do not know him, and they that doth not keep his Commands do not love him, How can it be expected that such should either love or know his Seed? Therefore we conclude, that where we finde any given up to pride and to seek after the honour of men which is not of God, or where we finde men given up to covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54755:14"/> or swearing, or lying, or whoredom, or drunkenness, or pleasure, or pastime, or in any works of darkness, that such neither love nor know Christ, the Light, the Truth, nor his Seed; and in this nature have we found many of the Ministers (so called) in <hi>England, viz.</hi> in pride, in covetousness, nay far more covetous then the Usurer, which will take but the double of his debt; but it is found that some of them hath taken and caused to be taken from them whom they have done no work for, of some, which by their Law could claim but a penny, yet they have taken a shilling; and where by their Law was due but a shilling; they have taken and caused to be taken forty shillings, these and such like practises are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable in the the sight of God, and they that doth allow or are found in and partaking with such like practises as these are shall assuredly come to Judgement, and the wrath of God shall assuredly fall upon them for it in its time.</p>
            <p>Therefore Friend consider the oppressions of the oppressed, which lyeth in Prisons and Holes for Truths sake, to wit, the Testimony of Jesus Christ their life, in them the Hope of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; Christ saith, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth and the Life, and there is none cometh to the Father but by me;</hi> Now the way to the Father is by the truth, now truth is light, and light is opposite to darkness, and he that is led by truth the light, which light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every man that cometh into the world, is kept out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but he that is in deceit is in darkness, and then not in the truth, but he that yieldeth up to the power of truth, there to stand, and by it to be guided, is out of deceit and in the light, which is Christ, and this Christ is in all that believe the Hope of Glory; hence it appeareth, That he that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by any other way then what is made known by the light which is Christ within, is in the deceit and in darkness, and knoweth not whether he goeth; Now as light is opposite to darkness, and truth to deceit, so they that regardeth not to listen to what Christ the Light in the heart makes known to them, are in darkness and goeth out of the way from the life into that which leadeth to death and destruction; Now Christ is the Way, the Truth and the Life, he came to reprove the world of sin in the heart, because he hath put his Law there, for the heart is it that God requires, if the heart delight to do the Will of God, that heart he accepts, and there he will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54755:14"/> dwell, but that heart that rejects reproof, and will not turn from that, for which Christ the light within in the heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it of, is found to reject Christ the Salvation of their Souls; for minde, a covetous mans heart delights in his goods, a swearer delights in swearing, a drunkard in drinking, for his delight is in it, a proud mans hearts delight is to see himself set above his equals, some men delight in honour as <hi>Haman</hi> did, and therefore hateth all in <hi>Mordecais</hi> nature; but let all such know that the Lord will turn all such down to dishonour, as <hi>Haman</hi> was, if they do not suddenly repent; some delight in pleasure in pastime, some in chambring in wantonness; Now the heart being the seat of delight, and it being filled with any of these delights which are works of darkness, there is no room for light, to wit, Christ in the Inn, but he must be turned out, and that by reason of the enmity betwixt them, for light cannot dwell with darkness nor darkness with light, for when Christ the light comes to appear in the dark heart, to reprove it of sin and evil, if not heeded, and what it is reproved of and for, returned from, then such turns from Christ the light, the Salvation, which would bring out of death and darkness into that which leadeth into destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Friend, consider what is set before thee to do, that is to walk before the Lord with a perfect heart, and that thou maist so do, thou art to take heed to the truth, the light Christ with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the heart, and let him be thy Counsellor in this thy day that is put into thy hand, for thou hast a power given thee whereby thou mayest overturn all the wicked intentions of all the evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded men in this Nation, which hath set themselves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Lord and his Annointed, the price of their lifes is put into thy hands, be faithful, the charge which thou hast put into thy hands as thou sittest at the stearn of Justice, is to see that Lawes be made in the fear of God, and according to his Will and Command, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat thou mayest so do, let thy Counsellor be the Lord of Hosts; and those that truly fear the Lord, and walk before him with a perfect heart, be the men that thou joynest in Counsel with, for they that truly fear the Lord dare not act any thing which may be for the dishonour of God, nor the suppression of any where the Seed of God is, which thou art required of the Lord to be careful
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54755:15"/> of, which may be known by their fruits; it is known what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is acted and put forth for Law, it will be in thy name; therefore it stands thee in hand to keep in the humility in which the Power of God stands, which will keep thee in that which shall stand against all that shall Counsel thee from that which shall be for the glory of God and the welfare of his People; for this know, that if any evil be acted in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Thou punish it not, a measure of the guilt shall be laid to thy charge; Therefore in this thy day fear before the Lord, for he is a dreadful God and a consuming fire before his adversaries, and become as a little child, and whilest the day is be thou faithful in thy labour and work, which is put into thy hand to do. <hi>Adam</hi> was once inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, but by reason of disobedience in yielding to the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Tempter, he was found in the transgression, was therefore drove from the presence of God where he was set; Christ was innocent, and was tempted by the Tempter, but he not yielding unto the temptation of the Tempter, was found faithful in obedience to the Will of his Father, and therefore received a Crown of Glory; Mark, thou art innocent of the many evils that hath been committed in this land, which hath been suffered to be done by the former higher Powers of this Nation, &amp; they being found in the disobedience, were cast out, and thou art now possessed in their places, and hast the same under thy hands they had; Mark, if thou keepest thy self in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent (and out of the evils which they suffered to be done) and be not overcome with the temptation of the Tempter, as <hi>Adam</hi> was, and they were, but resist the temptation of the Tempter as Christ did, thou wilt be found in so doing to do the Will of God, and abiding so to the end thou shalt receive thy measure of that honour which Christ had, and keeping to that humility which goeth before the honour which God gives, thou shalt see that the bodies and estates of men fearing God have a well being under thy Command; but know, that the Lord requires thee not to rule over the hearts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of men as unto things spiritual, for that is his place, and there he will place his Kingdom (know ye not that the Kingdom of Heaven is within you?) and he will make lawes for that Kingdom, it is written, he will write his law in the heart, And there it is that he requires obedience, and they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54755:15"/> that are obedient to what he requires there, they shall have favour in his presence, but they that disobey and rejects what he requires there, they shall receive the Rod of Correction; for such causes is our day made sad, and our oppression great, and our bodies exposed to what cruel minded men can do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us; for in pure obedience to what Christ Commands, which saith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> and because we cannot for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science sake swear when put upon it, we are made a prey of by people, which are many that abuses us, if we go to a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate and tell him of our abuses, they have demanded whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no we would give it in upon oath, the which for Christs sake we could not do, for this cause hath Justice been denied many of us, and the offender gone unpunished, &amp; we exposed to their mercies, which many of the dear Saints of God have found cruel upon them, for this cause hath some been depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for a time of their lands, and some their goods taken for fines, and some hath been cast in Prison.</p>
            <p>Therefore Friend consider, that as thou art brought by a high hand to be the chief Instrument which may overturn all the wicked intentions of all the evil-minded men in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as thou art set at the stearn of Justice, thy work is to see that Justice be executed right; the law was made for a praise to them that did well, and a terrour to them that did evil, which to do, it is required of thee to reform, and to put the sword of Justice into the hands of faithful and just men, such as in truth feareth God and departeth from iniquity; for this is seen and found that a covetous man, he through cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousness is fit to take a bribe, and that may blinde his eye so as he cannot alwayes see to do Justice; so a proud high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man is subject to respect persons, and regard a rich man for his riches and high esteem, by which means Justice may be turned backwards, and equity dye in the streets; for these and such like unjustnesse have we of late had large expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and for the evil which hath been acted against the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Consciences of many of the dear Saints of God, the land mourns and the Judgement of God hangs over, and hath in some measure seized upon some for their evil doings against the Elect and Chosen of God.</p>
            <p>Now Friend, to keep thy Conscience void of offence before God and all Just men, let it not enter into thy heart, as to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54755:16"/> obey, to suffer nor allow that any mans Conscience shall be tyed to any other way in the worship and service of God, then he by the light Christ within, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, shall lead him to do, and in so-doing thou shalt keep thy self innocent, and out of the breach of what thou hast promised, to wit, a liberty to tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, by which means thou shalt engage all that truly fear the Lord and walketh powerfully in his fight, to love, serve and obey thee with a single heart and an upright minde, and to be faithful unto thee as thou art faithful to the Lord.</p>
            <p>We are commanded that if any have a form of godliness and deny the power thereof, from such turn away, and to have no fellowship with unfruitful works of darkness: Now whereas a people may arise and say they are Christs, or of Christs flock, yet believe them not till thou hast tryed them, and that thou wilt do by taking away the cause, and when that is taken away, it will then be seen what the effects will be; deeply sensible am I made of thy present standing how slip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery it is, and being bound with the Cords of love to that measure of truth in thee, which none can take from thee, and as thy life is in the truth is my Joy and Peace; it is upon me by that measure of truth in me for truth sake, to inform thee what sad things is acted in thy name behinde thy back by some unjust Magistrates which are now in power, and that is to see the Just accused and punished falsly, and many unjust go free which are faulty; for if the words of an honest sober man may be taken, as soon as the oath of an unjust single person, there is some lies in Prison for words against thee that was not spoken by the persons so imprisoned, by which means some families are made uncapable of help to succour them with, but are exposed to great wants.</p>
            <p>Therefore I beseech thee as an Ambassadour in Christs stead for truths sake, that these things be suddenly inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after, and let truth have the upper hand, that all may be reformed and brought to the knowledge of that which Hell and Death cannot prevail against, and that door opened by which all may come to see what it is to have truth, the life, the power of Christ to rule and raign in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By one who is begotten to that truth, which keepeth faithful to the end all that abide in it</hi> JOHN SOWTER.</signed>
               <dateline>Written at <hi>Sutton</hi> in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi>
                  <date>in the 4th month called June 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54755:16"/>
            <head>AN ALARUM Beat in the Holy Mountain, That ENGLANDS Inhabitants may awake to Righteousness. Their Vanity and Prophaneness being here opened, that they may see what they have brought forth, and of what service it is to the KING or his Cause, unto whom they have pretended so much love. The KINGS safety and strength being here also plainly shewed, in a short Message of love unto him, which was delivered into his hands. <hi>By Commission from the Prince of Peace in W. S.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WIth you is my Controversie saith the Lord, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects my Councel and will none of my reproof, who goes on in Rebellion and hates to be Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, your wayes are all corrupt and your doings altogether evil, and your delight is therein placed; these things have I seen and have long held my peace, and you have thought that I have been such a one as your selves, but I will set your sins before you and cause you to remember your doings; my anger is kindled in my brest, and my jealousie burns like fire, my arm is stretched out and I will not gather it in until my work I have accomplished, and until I have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the intents of my heart, I have beheld you throughout, and my eye hath seen you in secret, your Councel you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54755:17"/> hide from me, for I am God and all my wayes are equal, your sins have long come up before me, &amp; the cry thereof hath been exceeding great, yet have I exercised patience towards you, and Judgement I have not executed speedily, but have forborn and suffered long, because my delight is in saving and not in destroying, but you have abused my mercy, and have not regarded the day of my patience, that my goodness might have led you to Repentance, but have hardned your faces to sin more and more, and saith the Lord sees not, neither is there knowledge in the Most High, but you shall all know that I have seen you and your doings, and will plead with you in the strength of my might, and by my hand you shall fall in Judgement, for I will scatter you and will not spare you, I will make you as dust before the winde, and then shall ye know that I am God, and all my Judgements Righteous, for I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect not persons in Judgement, neither regards the loftiness of man, but will bring him down to the dust and make him bow before my Power, both high and low, rich and poor shall know it who stands in their stout-heartedness, in the day when I do this saith the Lord God Almighty.</p>
            <p>O Inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> I have beheld you scattered as sheep without a shepherd, every man walking in his own way, and doing the thing that seems right in your own eyes, so that you are become exceeding sinful, and as a Cage of unclean birds, your deeds testifie against you that you are a rebellious people, stiff-necked and stout hearted, wilful and stubborn, sinning more and more, that the Lord is provoked, and his Spirit grieved with your unlawful deeds, and with the evil of your doings, for of late you have sinned as if you never could have sinned enough, that you have largely filled up the measure, and drawn the wrath of God near upon you, you have run desperately in the waies of darkness where your eyes are blinded that you cannot see your selves, so that iniquity you have greedily committed, and have exceedingly added to your former sins; Oh! turn to the measure of God that is manifest in you, that hath not joyned with you, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to your vanities, but hath stood a reprover of you in your own Conscience, turn unto it for it is pure light, and discovers every deed of darkness, wait in it and it will open your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings your wayes to behold, that you may loath what you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54755:17"/> have done, and depart from your evil wayes to turn to the Lord, whose way is pure, and his work holy, for you have been all cryed, the fence hath been pulled up, and you have been let loose, and hath had your swing, and into the height of vanity you have runned without stay, and hath made it manifest what your hearts delight in, sober people hath seen your folly, though you walk in darkness and doth not see your selves, you are so accustomed to do evil, and your delight is so placed in it, that you call it good, and esteems the man highly that is most exercised in it, and hath such a one in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect above others, that you count the proud happy, and those that do wickedly you honour, and none so much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected or esteemed by you, as they are; this is your own way, and you walk in it with delighting, and in your vain mindes are striving who should most exceed in prophaneness, and this is sufficiently evidenced in your rioting and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, pride and wantonness, for which the honest-hearted mourns, to behold the abominations and wickedness that is brought forth by you, and will certainly draw down the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord upon you, for your wickedness will fall upon your own heads, and this you shall know in the day when he executes vengeance, whom now you openly and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sins against; Oh! that your eyes were opened to see, and your understandings to perceive, that you might come into Gods fear, and dread his holy Name, for vengeance belongs unto him and he will repay, and though your day seem unto you as if no night should come upon you, yet know that you must come to Judgement and give an account of all your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, then will your day be dark and blackness will overspread you, and your faces will gather paleness when all the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards healths shall rise up against them and draw down wrath upon them, and increase their torment; this will be your portion, Oh ye drunkards of <hi>England,</hi> who now have your delight in it, that nothing is pleasing unto you but the vanity of it, nor none pleasing to your company but such as can joyn with you in it, and though your Cup seem to be filled with pleasure and with joy, and you drink all off with delightings, yet will the end be bitterness; Do you ever look into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, or consider what the last drop will be? Surely if ye were but so wise as to consider the last end, it would put a stop
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54755:18"/> unto you, and place Gods fear over you; for there is a Cup of indignation for you to drink, which will turn your joy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mourning, and your mirth into heaviness, and make you gnaw your tongues for pain, when your Cup of pleasantness shall be turned into bitterness, in the latter end this you shall know; how do you abuse Gods good creatures with your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderation and excess, until you make your selves uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of manhood, wallowing in the dirt and mire of your fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiness from day to day, rising up early to follow strong drink, and fit till night to be inflamed, and this you have followed with delightings, and hath made it your great busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, thinking your selves most in service when you were most in the excess, &amp; all this hath been presumed, &amp; with rejoycing practised in pretence of love to the King and his Cause, and you have charged the sober-minded with disaffection to the King and his Cause, upon no other ground but because they could not answer you in your vanity, nor run with you into the excess, and from this pretended zeal and affection to the King you have drawn encouragement to commit sin with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness, and it is upon me from the Lord to charge your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness upon your heads, that it may not lye upon the King nor his Cause, for desperate wickedness it is whatever you might pretend to be the ground for your practise, and you shall all know that you have sinned against the Lord of life and power, who is King of kings, and that you have dishonoured the King of the Nations, and as great enemies you are unto Him and his Cause as those that hath made wars against him, for your doings hath neither made him healthful nor happy, but hath rather added affliction to him, and by such a people his Throne cannot be established, for that which you have pretended to be in love to him now appears to be against him, and you have not expressed any love to Him or his Cause in those wayes wherein you have walked, but the enemy blinded your mindes, and raised up your vile affections to satisfie your own hearts lust, and then you made the King and his Cause your foundation; Oh! that your eyes were opened to see what you have done, and what you are doing, that you might come to repentance before it be too late, for the King is not honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nor his Cause advanced by your doings, so that your foundation is raced out, &amp; you are left without a bottom, for it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54755:18"/> is not expedient that the Kings Name should lye under your vanities and wickedness to uphold or support you in it, for the Load is revealing his Righteousness, and making known his Everlasting Truth and Holiness, which is more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable for the King to shew himself in, and to uphold and support as a nursing Father, and is his right place, and not to lye in the bottom of your dirt and mire in which you are wallowing, that is not his place, nor never can make him happy; so that you have spent your strength in vain and your labour to no purpose, and the sober people fathoms over you, whose love is after Truth and Righteousness, Justice and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is the honest Cause to be contended for and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and the King in it, that his Throne therein may be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished, which is the desire of all sober people, whose love is more to the King in Righteousness then yours is or can be in your wickedness, though they have and do deny your vanities, knowing that sin hath been the cause of ruine and desolation to King and Kingdomes, but never was the establishment of any; therefore you have begun at the wrong end, and must repent of all you have done before you can be the Kings friend in Truth, for all that you have gloried and is glorying in, is no way serviceable to the King or his Cause; What hath the King reaped by all your healths drinking? your kneeling upon your bare knees to do it, your throwing down your Hats upon the ground, and such excess, In which you have wronged your selves and degenerated from reasonable men, and no service at all have you done for the King in these things; What hath the King reaped by all your fires, which in the streets of most Towns in the Nation hath been kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? And this you have pretended, that it hath been done in your joy for the King, though nothing but sin and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, vanity and prophaneness hath been brought forth by you, that the Nation hath been on a flame with wildeness and madness in the exercise of these things; What doth the King reap by all your pride which you dock your selves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all? doth he profit any thing by all your Ribbons that you hang about you? or your Feathers that flyes about your Hats? or Gold or Silver Lace? Is there any service done to the King in setting up your long Poles in your Towns, and calls them May-poles? or doth the King reap any thing by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54755:19"/> your Piping and Fidling and Dancing about them? or your drinking or singing, or shouting? have you not laid the Kings name at the bottom of all this dirt and mire that stinks, and is so odious to all sober people? what have you expressed in all this either to the King or Kingdom? or what have you done? or wherein? or to whom stands your service? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but your folly have you manifested, neither fearing God, nor honouring the King; Therefore his strength doth not stand in you, neither is his safety in such a people, neither is there any thing that you have done or is doing that is any way serviceable to him, and what fruit he hath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by your doings he may well understand, for that which hath of late been practised in <hi>England,</hi> is not the way either to make a King happy or Kingdom blessed, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the Lords mercies from both, and draws down wrath and indignation upon King and Kingdom; and it may be read in the Scriptures of truth what hath made Kings happy and Kingdoms blessed, and what hath brought ruine and desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon them; for when the Lord was feared, and King and People did that which was right in his sight they were happy and blessed; but when they departed from him, and did that which was evil, he neither spared King nor people, and so hath the Lord alwayes recompenced both King and people in all ages and generations according to the fruits of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, for he that hath all power in his hand, and who ruleth over all the Kingdoms of the world, and whose they are, he pulls down, and he sets up, and he alone hath the Key to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and shut, and all that fears him and works Righteousness are accepted of him, and there is no respect of persons with him, and in the exercise of Righteousness, Truth and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness Kings are happy and Kingdoms blessed; but in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of wickedness and prophaneness, Kings and Governours will fall, and Kingdoms will be brought into desolation, and this generation have an evident Testimony of it, and may read it in the experience; how hath the Lords Arm been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised in his work, how hath he pulled down one and set up another within these few years past? because he was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, nor the trust which he reposed in them performed; therefore did he stretch forth his Arm, and at one blow laid them in the dust, for they were unfaithful, and when they had power to do good they did it not, though the Lord did
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54755:19"/> require it, but alwayes proved self-seekers and men pleasers, and waxed high and lifted up, and then stood ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lted and grew into those things which they destroyed in others, and so ruine and desolation in this Nation hath been felt thorow all fair shews and large pretences that hath been made from such as hath been in power, who never performed their Vowes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, nor what they promised in the day of tenderness, yet there is a remnant that God hath preserved in uprightness, who have walked in Gods fear and have waited upon him, and thorow all these changes they have learned Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, though multitudes in the Nation there yet be of whom it cannot be so said, but still abides in the vanity, and hath thorow all these changes waited for a day in which they might have an opportunity to satisfie their hearts lust, which now is broken forth; but you are all to be reproved, and without respect of persons you are hereby reproved and testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied against, and also warned from the Lord God to cease from your evil, for there is no profit in it, either to the King, the Kingdom, or your selves, for you are out of all truth, and from the Spirits manifestation that is given to profit withal, and so you can into errors, and doth not know the Scriptures nor the Power of God; Oh! foolish people and unwise, What will you do in the end of these things? Who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the Lord, and erred from his Spirit, and from the Scriptures of Truth; What Command or Example have you in the Scriptures for your doings? do you find in the Scriptures that the Christians ever practised such things as you do under any pretence whatsoever? can you shew it in any Chapter or Verse, that the Christians ran into excess, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of healths, and throwing down their Hats, and kneeling upon their knees <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> or that they were hung about with Ribbands, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> prickt about with Feathers, and making fires in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> called them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one fires, and set up long Poles in their Tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d called them May-poles, and then Piped and Danced, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ng and Singing, and Shout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Sporting in wildnes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> madness about them? is this the Christian state, or what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Christians practise, and what is their way they walk in? You have lost your understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and your sences is benummed with the custom of sin, that you are in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he far Countrey amongst the Heathen, &amp; bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54755:20"/> down unto their gods, and worshipping amongst their groves and graven Images, and yet bears the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, and can go to your named Church, and your profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed worship and hear your man-made Minister, and can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve all the Traditions, and bow to every Ceremony that man hath set up, and so you have professed Christianity many years; But doth not the root of a Christian bring forth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fruits then yours? You shame your Religion and your Ministry, who have been thus long learning of them, and they teaching of you day after day, and year after year, and you are but where you begun, if not worse many of you, you might have learned better things by all this teaching that you have had, you might not have been so ignorant of Truth and Righteousness, if your Ministers were of God, and placed amongst you by his Power, if you had been sober men and walked in Gods fear, you might have learned more Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in these years past in which some of you hath been exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised, and might have been sufficiently humbled, had you minded the Lord and his work, but you make it appear that you have not learned Righteousness, whose lives is wrapped up in sin and wickedness, and so the Heathen state abides, from which root all these evils springs; in all this time of teaching you might have learned more modesty and sobriety, and have brought forth some fruit that might have made your Ministers honourable, and adorned your profession with something of holiness, but you have lost the savour of all godliness, and degenerated into all manner of wickedness, and in your doings may your Ministers behold the fruit of their labour, to see you who are their constant hearers, filling the Town streets and spending your time in Drinking and Shouting, Piping and Dancing, as in many places of this Nation there is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Testimony from your own practise; this will fall upon the transgressors, and Gods witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s in your Conscience will rise against you and condemn you who are guilty of these evils, and it will clear and justifie the innocent and harmless, who have walked soberly in Gods fear; so that it will fall upon whom it is one, and it will pass over the heads of all sober people, and Gods witness in the Conscience of every one will either accuse or excuse in the particular, that all people in the Nation may truly see whether their hands or hearts
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54755:20"/> have been joyned unto the evils that have been acted and brought forth by many, or whether they stand cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves as before the Lord; so will the guilty be cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ned, and the innocent set free; and so whether Priest or People, old or young, you may all see your selves, and what lyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en you concerning these evils that is here testified against, for where the Priest is guilty Gods witness will not spare him, or where the rich and mighty is guilty it will not spare them, for it respects neither person nor title, but gives true Judgement against every transgressor, according to his deeds; Therefore all you Ministers of <hi>England</hi> search your hearts, for there is not many of you that Gods witness will clear, who had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your heart nor your hand joyned in these great and crying sins, either by promoting of them and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing with them, or secretly encouraging or countenancing the practise of them, that so there was not like to be a reproof given by you to stop them, when you was like minded with them and joyned with consent either openly or secretly; so the Scripture is fulfilled, like people like Priest, and for this hath the Lord a Controversie with you, because you have strengthened the hands of evil-doers, and hath not reproved sin in the Gate; therefore is the Lords hand against you, and he is rending your covering from off you, and he will leave you in the shame of your own nakedness, and make you a hissing to all that pass by, for you are deceitful workers, and your fruits makes you manifest, you are fair sayers but evil-doers, you love evil more then good, and pleasures more then God, and such examples are you amongst the people, the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion is ceased from you, and night is come upon you, that you have no answer of God; therefore you profit not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at all, but deceives them by your lyes and flatteries, and cryes Peace unto them when they are daily exercised in works of darkness, you have been weighed and truly tryed in the Spirit of Truth, and by the Scriptures of Truth, and you are found wanting, for the Life of Truth you are not in, nor the Life of Scriptures you do not live, the day hath declared you, your works is tryed; I do not mention these things to upbraid you, for that is not my life, but in pitty to you and all that are led by you and lives with you, <hi>I</hi> am constrained to warn you all to forsake the evil and chuse the good, to love
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54755:21"/> mercy, do justly and walk humbly with God, and turn to the Lord to his Power to feel; come within, search there, see your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> consider your doings, stand still, hear Gods voice, ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y his Councel, that what is past may suffice, for there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> profit in your doings, nor any service in your labour, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tead of wheat, tares spring forth, and instead of barley thistles grow, and this is the fruit of your labour, and the end of your harvest; Therefore Priest and People, high and low, rich and poor consider your states, for the ground is known by the Crop that it brings forth, and the tree is known by its Fruit, and now the Ax is laid unto the root, and the tree that brings not forth good fruit it must fall by the stroke, and the fire is its place; this tree is in your selves, the savour of your fruit doth plainly declare it, the Ax is laid, the stroke is near you, and God will not spare you of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree soever you are, but by his hand you must fall if you go on in your wickedness; and now you are all warned, and I am cleared before the Lord concerning you, and whether you hear or forbear, the Alarum is true in the day you shall know it.</p>
            <p>Unto thee O King a Message of love I have, and from the Lord it is laid upon me, and in faithfulness unto him I must declare it; Incline thy ear with meekness, and let patience be thy covering, for the Lord God is mighty, and his presence is dreadful, he it is that opens my heart and directs my speech unto thee; trust thou in God O King, and delight thy heart in him alone, that he may be the length of thy dayes, and the strength of thy life, for thou art but a mortal man and cannot stand without the Lords upholding, thy life is in his hand, and thy Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in his power, for he gives and takes at his pleasure, he hath placed thee in dignity and hath given thee power over three Nations, and thy Dominion extendeth thorow three Kingdoms, in which there is a great and mighty People, and they are variously affected in Judgement, the eyes of all are upon thee, and great is the expectations of many; therefore wait thou upon God O King, and joyn unto the Principle of life, and unto it alwayes resort for Councel, that thou mayest go in and out before so great and mighty a People, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster true Judgement un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o every one in their present state, so
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54755:21"/> will thy way prosper, and thou wilt be happy, for God hath for a time proved thee and thy patience, and now hath brought thee into dignity, and he expects fruit from thee; he tryed many before thee who had power to do good, and made large promises, but they neglected and did not answer the Lord in faithfulness, so their day suddenly passed over, and he cut them off and laid them waste, and they are no more; And now it is thy day, Power thou hast and God expects thy faithfulness, wait to perform unto the Lord that what others carelesly neglected, and for which cause they were overturned, thou mayest in this thy day fulfil; Therefore be circumspect O King, for the matter is weighty, and joyn to the Principle of God which is pure, and it will lead thee into Gods pure Councel, and unite thee to him and all that fear him, which can onely make thee happy, and this will be strength unto thee, and safety for thee, upon which if thou layest hold thou dost well; for if thou cleave unto the Lord and wait upon him in uprightness, he will not forsake thee, but will be wisdom to thee, in which thou wilt be able to order the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aright, and to place true Judgement in the earth, that it will run down like a stream from the true Fountain, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide betwixt the pretious and prophane, and here will every Soul be subject to thy Power, not onely for fear but also for Conscience sake; and in thy Government the Righteous will rejoyce, as in the Power of God thou stands to be a praise unto the good, and a terrour unto the evil, and in this thou wilt be happy, and thy way will prosper; But if thou erre from the Lord, and depart from his Councel, and hearken unto men, and place thy confidence in their strength, thou wilt not prosper, for that hath been the fall of many, who never could rise again when they placed confidence in mens Councels and strength, and regarded not the Councel of the Lord; therefore in love is this Message unto thee O King; and this is the Way in which thou art to walk, be stayed upon the Lord, and wait his wisdom to receive, that thou mayest truly understand the state of the people over whom thou art placed, and strive not to please parties, but minister a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of true Judgement unto all, thou hast the sword in thy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54755:22"/> hand, wait to be a Minister of God for good, break off the bonds of oppression of what nature soever, undo all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burdens which tender Consciences cannot bear; give true freedom in the practise of Religion, let none be compelled to worship is any form contrary to their freedom, mix not thy power with the Lord in such things, leave his own work to him, that what pertains to the Conscience he may order, for he is the Searcher and knows secrets, and it belongs to him; Break off every yoke that doth oppress the innocent, let all forcing and compelling, and suing of those that are tender, and cannot for Conscience sake conform to any thing ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Truth, be wholly removed, that in matter of worship the tender Conscience may not any way be entangled, who in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things lives peaceably and quietly under thy Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; these, with many other things the Lord requires of thee, which unto thee belongs, and which thou art to see effectually done, for the Lord will redeem his Chosen; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have had their day to have done it, but were careless, and the Lord hath smitten them, &amp; blasted them; &amp; now thou hast thy day and power to perform it, be diligent to obey the Lord, that he that hath set thee up to try thee, may not have cause to pull thee down, for at his pleasure he can do it, if thou be not careful to perform uprightly what he requires of thee; and do thou shew mercy unto all, and seek not revenge upon any, though thou mayest apprehend much wrong hath been done, yet do thou forgive it, for it could not have come to pass but in the permission of God; so do thou leave it to him, that he may Judge who Judges Righteously, &amp; truly gives a just recompence of reward unto every man; and so shew thy self merciful, as God hath shewed mercy unto thee, that in love a perfect unity of hearts may be amongst all people under thy Government, and this will make thee truly honourable and happy, and give thee the necks of all thine enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee, and peace within thy borders will abound, and all the people will be towards thee unfeignedly; therefore be single to the Lord O King, and encline thine ear to his Councel, that his pure light in thy Conscience may be thy guide, and that the power thereof thou mayest submit unto, which will
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54755:22"/> keep thee in a clear understanding, and give thee a true discern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, both of thy own state &amp; the state of the people over whom thou art placed; and as thou waits the light to obey and abide in, thou wilt be made able to search into deep matters &amp; secret causes, &amp; to minister true Judgement with a pure understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; And be tender over a poor and afflicted people, who travels within thy Dominion and Preaches Peace thorow the Nations, who amongst the many names have a Name given by the world, &amp; are by the people thereof called <hi>Quakers,</hi> they are born of the Royal Seed, &amp; the Lord is their God, and he hath chosen them to be his People in Righteousness, their delight is to do his Will and to be subject unto his Power, Mercy &amp; Truth they love, Righteousness, Peace and true Justice their heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, many hath oppressed them, but few hath been mindful of them to shew them any favour, they have been a suffering People thorow times and changes, and hath endured and born affliction in patience, the love of God is manifest in them, and a willing People they are made unto him, for his love con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strains and draws them after him, and they are freely given up unto him and dare not deny him, though all people should set themselves against them, let thy care be over them, for they are the flock of God, and the Apple of his Eye, and if thou shew favour and love unto them, and take off the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and all the yokes from off them, the Lord will bless thee; but if thou sleight them, and have not regard unto them, but suffer the Oppressors still to oppress them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the yoke upon them, &amp; make thy loyns as heavy as others have been before thee, he that hath set thee up and placed thee, he will pull thee down and remove thee, and there will be none found to uphold thee; this is weighty O King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider it in coolness.</p>
            <p>Beware of men and of their Councels, for there is much deceit, and many will work upon thee for their ends, that they may come into honour and dignity, many such thou wilt find near thee.</p>
            <p>There is a people that hath not swarved from thee, but hath suffered under the power of others for thy sake, these will come near thee, and there is some cause that thou shouldst shew
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54755:23"/> respect unto them, but beware thou give not thy strength unto them, for many of them is after vanity, which the Lord is not pleased with; therefore cast not thy self upon them, least thou fall in their hand.</p>
            <p>There is another sort of people who have not been faithful to any cause, but have sought themselves thorow all the Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions that hath come to pass, who stood against thee in the day when others had strength and power, and now appears for thee, and shews themselves to be great friends to thee; cast not thy self upon such a people, for they will betray thee, and if thou lean upon them, they will let thee fall.</p>
            <p>When things are searched to the bottom, thy way is a strait way O King, and none can uphold thee in it but the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; therefore cast thy self upon him, place thy confidence in him, and walk thou in his fear and in uprightness before him, and he will be strength unto thee, and safety for thee; so in the Lord and in his People whom he hath chosen from amongst the many people, thy strength and safety is O King, hither turn, come trust and believe in the Invisible, Life and Power is in him, Dominion and Victory he gives at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, not by Sword nor Spear, but in the might of his own Spirit, which in this day he hath abundantly made manifest, and by which his chosen People are guided, which is their Strength and Life, their Joy and Salvation; if thou wouldst have strength turn in hither, if thou wouldst be safe lay hold, come, here cast thy self, and place thy confidence; and though neither Sword nor Spear, nor host of men appear to be on thy side, the Prayers of the Righteous shall prevail for thee, who hath access to the Throne of Grace; and as thou hast Faith in this, though it may seem weak, yet thou shalt know that it is stronger then all weapons of War, to give the Victory and establish thee and the Kingdoms in perfect Peace.</p>
            <p>Let the Cry of the Innocent come before thee, and let their Cause be considered by thee, who suffers in bonds this day within thy Dominions, for no other Cause but for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science sake, reach forth relief unto them, free them and release them by thy Order O King; so will thy Name be a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54755:23"/> sweet savour, and God will be with thee and bless thee, and happy wilt thou be for ever if thou encline thine ear to the Lords Councel, and perform what he requires of thee in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightness of thy heart. In submission to the Power of God, is this Message of love written unto thee O King,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By one who truly honours the Lord, and thee in the Lord.</hi> WILLIAM SMITH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>BE it known unto thee <hi>O King,</hi> That since thy departure out of this Nation, there hath been not onely many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions and Overturnings, mutations and changes among them that have been invested with the Government of this Nation, but there hath also been much strife and contention, variance and Disputation among the Inhabitants of it about <hi>Religion:</hi> And in the midst of all this, the Lord God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth hath made his Power known unto a Remnant whom he hath gathered out of the many Wayes, Forms, Worships, and Customes, which the Nation is found in; and with them the Nation hath been <hi>Angry,</hi> and they have been abhorred and despised above any other people in the Nation: Yea, all the Sects in the Nation have opposed them, Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together against them, and they have been as <hi>A Rock of offence, or as a burthensome Stone</hi> even unto them all; Yet know this <hi>(O King,)</hi> that the Lord hath blessed them, and greatly multiplyed them, and for their sakes he hath <hi>Rebuked</hi> many that have oppressed them, and would not let them go free.</p>
            <p>Now that which chiefly lies upon me at presene, is to give thee a brief description of those people, to whom (as yet) thou art but a <hi>Stranger,</hi> by reason of thy long absence out of the Nation: And first, They are such a people as are sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the Power and Spirit of the Lord from the National Churches, National Ministry, National way of Worship; and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54755:24"/> they own that Church <hi>which is in God the Pillar and ground of Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th;</hi> and that Ministry which is the gift of God, by and from his Spirit in those that are ordained of him, and sent forth by him <hi>to preach the Gospel freely;</hi> and that Worship they own, which <hi>is in Spirit and in Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They are such as cannot give flattering Titles unto men, nor respect mens persons, nor Worship them, neither can they honour them, by giving them flattering Titles, nor by bowing their knees unto them, and standing uncovered before them: And this is one great cause wherefore men are so much offended at them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are such as abide in Christs Doctrine, and keeps to <hi>Yea and Nay in their Communication,</hi> and cannot <hi>Swear at all;</hi> but have chused rather to have been fined for not Swearing, then they (by Swearing) will break the Command of Christ, who saith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. They are such as do not seek to be avenged of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary; for when they are wronged by having <hi>their goods spoiled,</hi> by being falsly imprisoned, and shamefully intreated by wicked men; these things (for the Truths sake) they pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently suffer, knowing <hi>that Vengeance belongs to the Lord, and he will repay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. They are such as cannot manifest their joy, when they have cause to rejoyce, by devouring so much Fuel with one <hi>Bone-fire,</hi> as would serve some Family a whole year; neither dare they lay out their money for Ringing of <hi>Bells,</hi> and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishly spend their labour in such like things which are unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and vain; neither can they manifest their respect unto thee, by making themselves drunk <hi>with drinking thy Health,</hi> and afterwards burn their Hats, and other of their Raiment, as several have done since thou wast Proclaimed: Nay, their Righteous souls thereby are vexed, and their spirits grieved with beholding those things, which adds to the Creations burden.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They are such as cannot side with Parties in their Plots and Conspiracies one against another, in their destroying and cutting off one another; but chuseth rather to suffer by them all, then partake with any of them in their evil deeds: Yet so
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54755:24"/> far as they see any act for God, by being <hi>a terrour to evil doers, and a praise to them that do well,</hi> so far they can own them, what denomination soever they go under, or for whom soever they pretend to be.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They are such as have suffered by all Powers that have been the Supream in the Nation since they were a People, chiefly for several of the things before-mentioned; &amp; they take much notice how the generality of people can comply with, and conform unto all Powers, and even all men that are set up to be the Supream among them: One while they will be for those that are for <hi>a Common-wealth,</hi> in words pretending to hazard both their Lives and Estates on their behalf against <hi>a King, or single Person, &amp;c.</hi> But if a change come, and that Party be worsted, for whom they pretended to be so zealous, then will they (in words) be as vehement against them, as they were zealous for them. Now what Confidence can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>King or Parliament</hi> put in such men, as will first engage to one Partie, and then to another, and yet prove true and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant to neither? But with those People whom God hath blessed, and of whom I write, it is not so; for, <hi>Their Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is not in the Arm of Flesh, but in the living God, who hath all Power in his hand, and who alone will Rule in the Kingdoms of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be it also known unto thee <hi>(O King,)</hi> That if I should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate to thee in every particular wherein these people do differ from the generality of men, time would fail me, and I also fear that I should weary thee: This one thing shall I therefore the rather desire of thee, <hi>(viz:)</hi> That if thou desire to know upon what ground these People do such and such things, and what is the Reason that they omit the doing of such and such things as before-mentioned; then shew thy <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> in giving <hi>Audience</hi> to some two or more of them, that might be admitted into thy Presence, to make their <hi>Defence</hi> before thee against any of their Opposers, that may have any thing to charge against them: For I suppose thou maiest have heard many reports of them, and oftentimes false reports are blazed abroad concerning them, thereby to make them odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto the Nation, and Nations round about: Wherefore be thou perswaded with King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> who when he heard
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54755:25"/> strange things reported of <hi>Paul,</hi> said, <hi>I would also hear the man my self;</hi> So, chuse rather to hear them make their defence in thy Presence, then strengthen the hands of Evil-doers against them, who hath made a Prey upon them for several years past and the thing hath not been laid to heart, by them that have had the Supream Power in their hand, who have had <hi>their day,</hi> but now they are removed out of the Way, and <hi>Thy day</hi> is come, wherein the Lord is determined to try thee, as hee hath done them that are gone before thee: Wherefore (O King <hi>Love Mercy, do Justice, and walk humbly before the Lord,</hi> lest thy daies <hi>be troublesom;</hi> And be not lifted up with the Pomp and vanitie of this World, which will perish and have an end, but be rather Meek and Humble, that it may be well with thee, and that with Wisdom thou may be indued from above, therewith to order the affairs of thy Realm aright, to the praise and glory of him, <hi>who is King of kings, and Lord of lords,</hi> to whom be Honour and Dominion for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Written by a Servant of the Lord, who is known unto many by the name of</hi> WILLIAM CATON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>This was written (to the King) about the time of his comming in.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:54755:25"/>
            <head>A WORD Of tender Admonition to King Charles the II. And to this present PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT laid upon me a Servant of the Lord, in his Name and fear to warn you that you take heed of seeking revenge, or having a hand in the blood of those who are now brought under your power; for since that the Lord hath thus long spared the King, and in patience towards him hath thus much answered his desires, that he is come into power and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out shedding of blood, he and you ought to take heed of now beginning to shed blood and seeking revenge, least the Angel of the Lord (the Avenger of blood) go forth against you; so that it concerns you to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them that in times past were stirred up against the King and his party, and to pass by their former offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and wherein they are guilty of offending the Lord in any of their proceedings, leave it to the Lord to take vengeance since that you are set over them, for vengeance is the Lords and he will repay, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.35. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19, 20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.21, Mercifulness and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54755:26"/> patience towards all would be a comely Ornament to you both in the sight of God and men, for that hath been too much wanting both among Rulers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which hath made the Nation at that confused pass it hath long been in; and you know not how God may yet turn the Wheel, either with or against you, according to your faithfulness or unfaithfulness to him, nor how soon you may be brought under your Adversaries, if you should provoke the Lord to wrath thorow seeking revenge; therefore for you to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give offences and not to seek revenge, but he compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionate would be of good report, and a means to cool and moderate the spirits of the Kings Adversaries, when the contrary will but agravate and stir up more mischief; and if you ask of God to forgive you your trespasses as you forgive them that trespass against you, How can you expect forgiveness at the hand of God, if you do not forgive them that have trespassed against you? For blessed are the merciful, they shall obtain mercy, Mat. 5.7.</p>
            <p>And Friends, take heed how you go about to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish Priests by a Law over the Nation, to bring all under them in matters of Religion and Worship, or to bring the whole Nation to an uniformity in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, for there are many differences, and many sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry perswasions in the mindes of the people of this Nation, and yet generally they see beyond both Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, Episcopal Ministers (so called) and the Papists, &amp; thousands do see through the corruptness of them all, both in many of their Principles and Practises, which are contrary to the practises of the true Ministers, who feared God and hated covetousness; so that to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish the Priests by a Law, to Lord it over mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, and to bear Rule over the people of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by their means, and to preach for hire as the false
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54755:26"/> Priests and Prophets did, <hi>Isa.</hi> 56.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.28, 29, 30, 31. cannot be owned nor born by many, neither will that establish the Nation in Peace, but cause further distraction; and also this would reflect upon the People of God, and burthen his Seed which is of great weight in this Nation, which God is gathering thousands to, that he may be their Law-giver and the Defender of their Faith and Establisher of their Religion, and not man; for it is not in mans will to do, but Gods Work, which he hath begun in this Nation.</p>
            <p>And the same Spirit of Truth wherein God is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped, must perswade men into the true Religion, and guide them in their worship, for it is the Spirit of Truth that must lead men into all Truth, <hi>John</hi> 4.23. and 16.13. And Christ must have the preheminence, whom the people are to hear in all things, and they that will not hearken unto him must be destroyed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15, 18. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. and 7.37. So the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> pertaining to God to do, as the establishing Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> &amp; the bringing men into the form and power of Truth in Worship and Religion leave you to God to do, and let the people be left free to him to order in that case, and discharge your Consciences in things pertaining to you that are the nearest you, as in removing oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and preserving the Nations in their Civil Rights &amp; Liberties, that what is good in all sorts of professors and people may be answered, and mercifulness and tenderness may be used towards all, for that is it we desire, and not to set up any Ministers to Tyrannize over the Nation, nor to Lord it over tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, nor to persecute men that differ from them, and make spoil of their goods as they have long done, which is a grief to the Lord and to his annointed Seed, which must Rule and Reign, and be King and Priest and Law-giver in his Church, for he will not give his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54755:27"/> Glory to another; and all that oppose his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Consciences of his People shall be broken to pieces and confounded, who would limit and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men from Christ the true Priest and Teacher with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to an Usurping, Tyrannizing and Persecuting Priesthood without, who like the Papists would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute men for Religion, and like the Jews and false Priests among them, who builded up <hi>Zion</hi> with blood, and Jerusalem with iniquity, <hi>Mica</hi> 3.10, 11. who were in the killing nature, and not in the nature of Christ, who came not to destroy mens lives, but to save them; and the King may be sensible how the hand of the Lord appeared against these Priests, in that he would not suffer them to drive on their corrupt designes former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the Priests of <hi>Scotland</hi> (whose Cruelty and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as well as the Episcopal men is clearly discovered) who would have had the King to have established their Presbyterian Government over the Nations, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> would have been as Tyrannical as the Episcopal Government (so called) upon which the Lord stirred up enemies against them; which now may be a warning to him and you, that you take heed of setting up that perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting lordly spirit of the Priests to Lord it in the Nation, and to bring all under it, least you fall &amp; come into contempt as others before you have done, for their coming under the same persecuting spirit of the Priests; for the Lord God of Life and Power will not bear it, that either Presbyterian Priests, Episcopal Priests, or Popish Priests should be set up to usurp over mens Consciences, and to Tyrannize over the Nation; also if any sort of these should so be set up over the people to Tyrannize and Compell all to your worship, all that differ from them would be set in their hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, and many would be as one body against them, and the Lord in his Judgement would appear
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54755:27"/> both against them for their Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anny, and the Setters of them up in it, for God is a God of knowledge, and by him art actions weighed, and his Controversie with this Nation is not yet ended, for the Oppression, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, Pride and Iniquity which is broken forth in it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Lord, who will break the Horn of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and bring down the pride of men, and great will be the fall of them that reject his light in their Consciences, and lift up themselves in their pride and vain glory against the Lord and his annointed Seed.</p>
            <p>This in Compassion and Mercy was I moved to write unto thee O King and the Parliament, that whilest you have a day you may take warning and minde the Counsel of the Lord in the Light of his Son in you, that you intrude not into things that are too high for you, nor set up Persecutors (whom the Lord will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow) over the Consciences of people, least your day suddenly pass over, and you fall in the night with them that fall.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From one who desires not the death of any in their sins, but rather that they may return and live.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>the 6th of the 6th Month, 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
               <p>AND if any of the Priests do inform the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us called <hi>Quakers,</hi> or against our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples behind our backs, whereby to instigate thee O King to persecute us (as we know such hath been their practise from time to time) it is but a reasonable thing that thou hear both parties face to face, that we may know what our Accusers can accuse us of to our faces, that we may answer them, and both parties be heard without partiality; for we know that many are the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54755:28"/> slanders that the Priests have invented against us in their persecuting spirit; so that this was upon me to lay before the King, that we are free to vindicate any Principle we hold, and to manifest the Truth of it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures of Truth; And this in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular for the Truths sake I am willing to be answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to, if I be lawfully called to it, as God shall make way and enable, that so the Truth may be manifested, and all occasions of evil surmizings and false suspitions may be removed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>